<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE pkgmetadata SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/metadata.dtd">
<pkgmetadata>
  <maintainer type="person">
    <!-- Only for this ebuild on the oiledmachine-overlay -->
    <!-- Send bug reports or feature request to same overlay -->
    <email>orsonteodoro@hotmail.com</email>
  </maintainer>
  <maintainer type="project">
    <!-- Originator -->
    <email>genkernel@gentoo.org</email>
  </maintainer>
  <longdescription>
  <![CDATA[
    This is an ebuild fork that applies subdir_mount, crypt_root_plain, CFI,
    Clang PGO support patches.

    Patch status:
    3.5.x.x - subdir_mount (works), crypt_root_plain (works)
    4.0.x - subdir_mount (untested), crypt_root_plain (works), llvm (works)
    4.2.x - subdir_mount (untested), crypt_root_plain (works), llvm (works),
      pgo (done, but may expand for a few more benchmarks.  Testing
      was not done yet to confirm that there was a performance gain before
      and after.),  cfi (builds sucessfully, but needs testing of it
      actually working), plausable-deniable-dmcrypt-plain (in development)

    When switching between 4.2.x and older versions, The /dev/disk/by-id/
    entries may change.  This means that you need to adjust the kernel
    parameters to the correct identifiers.

    CFI support is limited to arm64 and x86_64 at this time.  arm64 is
    upstreamed completely, but x86_64 CFI support is currently in
    development/testing and requires manual patching.  The reference
    section below contains links to the x86_64 patches and how to add them
    as a per-package user patch, or you can wait until they are merged
    mainline.

    Some PGO trainers require you run them in a desktop environment.

    If we used automation, we could possibly reduce steps 2-4 within
    about 90 minutes.

    Estimated time to build:

    30 min to build the instrumented kernel.
    30 min to run training to generate a profile.
    30 min to build the optimized kernel.

    PGO support requires a PGO toolchain to run benchmarks.  All benchmarks
    are done on a live system to make it more accessible without getting
    too technical.

    The following steps must be take for a PGO kernel:

    (1) Emerge a source based kernel package >= 5.13 with applied PGO and profraw compat patches
        (See references section below for how to obtain and apply patches)
    (2) Run genkernel --pgi all (with menuconfig if you didn't set the profraw version)
    (IMPORTANT:  if You still need to change the kernel config with the supported profraw version.)
    (3) Reboot
    (4) Run genkernel --pgt-all train
    (optional) Run genkernel --pgt-yt train in X as a normal user
    (5) Run genkernel --pgo all
    (6) Reboot

    The trainers that you choose should reflect typical use.  You may also
    extend PGO with your own custom script.  The script should be placed
    in /usr/share/genkernel as pgo-custom.sh in the same folder as gen_pgo.sh
    with 0770 permissions with wheel to both user or group ownership.

    Due to licensing concerns for the 2014 PGO GCC patch and associated scripts
    cannot be integrated both in the kernel sources and this package
    directly.  Only the 2021 Clang PGO patchset will be supported.

    Environment variables:

      Store them in /etc/genkernel.conf or wrapper script.
      
      PGO_P2P_URI - The URI must have a filename to replace the placeholder
                    torrent.  (Only public domain assets or open source project
                    torrents should be used.)

      PGO_TRAINER_NETWORK_TCP_CONGESTIONS - string separated list from
        /proc/sys/net/ipv4/tcp_allowed_congestion_control to select for
        PGO training.

      PGO_FILESYSTEMS_LIST - a string separated list of selected
        quintuples in this format to PGO train:

          ioscheduler_name&fs_name&dev_name&mount_point&test_dir

        * io_scheduler_name must be one of the names listed in
          `cat $(find /sys/devices/ -path "*sda*scheduler")`, where sda is
          replaced with the block device of interest.  It will be used to switch
          to that scheduler.
        * fs_name must match the driver name.  These are listed in
          ${KERNEL_DIR}/fs as one the subdirectories.
        * dev_name must the basename to the corresponding path listed in
          find /sys/ -name "scheduler".
        * mount_point must be abspath to the mount point.  It must not contain
          a space in the abspath.
        * test_dir must be a decent size folder like similar to /usr/bin that
          is used for grep tests and sequential read tests.  It also is
          an abspath relative to mount_point.  Read only tests are only
          performed in this directory.

        Example:
        PGO_FILESYSTEMS_LIST="bfq&ext4&sda&/&/usr/bin kyber&bfs&sdb&/mnt/foo&/data mq-deadline&ext4&sda&/&/usr/bin"

        If it is not set, it will default to the following:
        PGO_FILESYSTEMS_LIST="unk&unk&unk&/&/usr/bin"

      PGO_TRAINER_YT_URI - a custom URI to a video.  By default it
      will show a sample of the 2021 USA inauguration.

    References:

      PGO patch:
      https://git.kernel.org/pub/scm/linux/kernel/git/kees/linux.git/patch/?h=for-next/clang/pgo&id=a15058eaefffc37c31326b59fa08b267b2def603&id2=fca41af18e10318e4de090db47d9fa7169e1bf2f

      PGO patch commit history:
      https://git.kernel.org/pub/scm/linux/kernel/git/kees/linux.git/log/?h=for-next/clang/pgo

      profraw v6 to v8 compat patch:
      https://raw.githubusercontent.com/orsonteodoro/oiledmachine-overlay/master/sys-kernel/ot-sources/files/clang-pgo-support-profraw-v6-to-v8.patch

      cfi-x86-v3 patch
      https://github.com/torvalds/linux/compare/d0ee23f9...samitolvanen:x86-cfi-v3.patch

      cfi-x86-v3 unload module fix.
      https://raw.githubusercontent.com/orsonteodoro/oiledmachine-overlay/master/sys-kernel/ot-sources/files/cfi-x86-cfi_init-ifdef-module-unload.patch

      cfi-x86-v3 commit history
      https://github.com/torvalds/linux/compare/d0ee23f9...samitolvanen:x86-cfi-v3

      Instructions for applying per-package user patches:
      https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki//etc/portage/patches
  ]]>
  </longdescription>
  <use>
    <flag name="cfi">Ensure that the Code Flow Integrity toolchain requirements
      are met.</flag>
    <flag name="crypt_root_plain">Adds dmcrypt plain support.
      This version of the patch will be deprecated due to design flaws
      concerning plausable deniability.
      </flag>
    <flag name="cryptsetup">Enable support for Luks disk encryption using
      <pkg>sys-fs/cryptsetup</pkg></flag>
    <flag name="firmware">Prefer system firmware
      <pkg>sys-kernel/linux-firmware</pkg> over local copy.</flag>
    <flag name="entry">Replaces the vanilla entry access
      with a customizable one.</flag>
    <flag name="llvm">Enable support for the Clang/LLVM toolchain
      These changes only apply to building the kernel only.</flag>
    <flag name="lto">Ensure that the Link Time Optimization toolchain
      requirements are met.</flag>
    <flag name="pgo-clang">Add clang PGO support to genkernel.</flag>
    <flag name="pgo-custom">Add a PGO custom script to genkernel
      to PGO train unconventional portions of the kernel or whatever
      you want.</flag>
    <flag name="pgo_trainer_crypto">Trains the Crypto API portion of the
      kernel.</flag>
    <flag name="pgo_trainer_memory">Trains the memory portion of the kernel
      subsystem.</flag>
    <flag name="pgo_trainer_network">Trains network portions of the kernel
      downloading a few bytes of the kernel and ICMP/UDP PGO training.</flag>
    <flag name="pgo_trainer_p2p">Trains the network, filesystem, disk portions
      of the kernel subsystems using peer-to-peer (p2p) with a open source
      project archive.</flag>
    <flag name="pgo_trainer_webcam">Trains webcam portions of the kernel that
      may contain software based implementations on cheap cameras.</flag>
    <flag name="pgo_trainer_xscreensaver_2d">Train the CPU scheduler, GPU
      portions of the kernel using 2D drawing primarily with complex graphics or
      computational geometry algorithms.  It will spawn ncores*thread_per_core
      processes.  Best used with an auto tile tiling window manager so that
      tricks are not applied to skip rendering.</flag>
    <flag name="pgo_trainer_xscreensaver_3d">Train the GPU portions of the
      kernel with OpenGL ~1.3.  It will spawn ncores * thread_per_core
      processes.  Best used with a auto tile tiling window manager so that
      tricks are not applied to skip rendering.</flag>
    <flag name="pgo_trainer_yt">Trains the kernel code paths that use
      the network, audio, graphics with streaming video.</flag>
    <flag name="shadowcallstack">Ensure that the shadow-call-stack toolchain
      requirements are met</flag>
    <flag name="subdir_mount">Adds mounting subdirectory support.  Used for
      mounting muslx32 or stage2 or stage3 images in place produced from
      crossdev and mounting them directly at /usr/$CTARGET without risk of
      damage caused by human error replacing / with /usr/$CTARGET.
    </flag>
    <flag name="sudo">Allow use of sudo to mark non-root PGO training
      complete</flag>
    <flag name="steghide">Allow to access the password keyfile into
      an audio or image file to improve dm-crypt crypt plain
      plausable deniablity.
    </flag>
  </use>
  <!--
    <upstream>
    <remote-id type="gentoo">git://git.gentoo.org/proj/genkernel</remote-id>
  </upstream>
  -->
  <upstream>
    <remote-id type="sourceforge">fuse</remote-id>
  </upstream>
</pkgmetadata>
