<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pkgmetadata SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/metadata.dtd">
<pkgmetadata>
  <!-- only in this ebuild fork on the oiledmachine-overlay -->
  <maintainer type="person">
    <email>orsonteodoro@hotmail.com</email>
    <name>Orson Teodoro</name>
  </maintainer>
  <!-- originator -->
  <maintainer type="project">
    <email>chromium@gentoo.org</email>
    <name>Chromium in Gentoo Project</name>
  </maintainer>
  <longdescription>
    Chromium is the open-source web browser project behind Google
    Chrome

    For this ebuild fork, you can build 32 bit Chromium on 64 bit.
    Multiple ABI installation is in testing.  This will allow to use
    binary only plugins that support a major ABI and allow to
    continue to use the experimental ABI as the default.

    You need to add the following in /etc/portage/profile/package.use.force
    in order to select a non-native ABI.  Tweak below to add your masked ABI.
    ----- CUT BELOW HERE -----
www-client/chromium -abi_x86_64 -abi_x86_32 -abi_x86_x32 -abi_mips_n64 -abi_ppc_64 -abi_s390_64
    ----- CUT ABOVE HERE -----
  </longdescription>
  <upstream>
    <bugs-to>https://www.chromium.org/for-testers/bug-reporting-guidelines</bugs-to>
  </upstream>
  <use>
   <flag name="component-build">Split build into more shared libraries to speed
     up linking. Mostly intended for debugging and development, NOT RECOMMENDED
     for general use.</flag>
   <flag name="hangouts">Enable support for Google Hangouts features such as
     screen sharing</flag>
   <flag name="headless">Build Ozone only with headless backend, NOT RECOMMENDED
     for general use.</flag>
   <flag name="libcmalloc">Use the allocator provided by the libc implementation.
     With glibc malloc (ptmalloc2 based) memory reuse is wastefully duplicated
     between threaded arenas especially for large data.  However, the glibc
     allocator is widely used and tested.</flag>
   <flag name="js-type-check">Enable JavaScript type-checking for Chrome's web
     technology-based UI. Requires Java.</flag>
   <flag name="official">Enable Official build instead of Developer build.</flag>
   <flag name="partitionmalloc">Use PartitionAlloc as the default allocator and
     replacement to tcmalloc.  It's designed for more for security and low
     latency, and benefits most from memory use effiency.  It is actively being
     improved which may present newer bugs.  It's the default in 92 and later.
     </flag>
   <flag name="pic">Disable optimized assembly code that is not PIC
     friendly</flag>
   <flag name="proprietary-codecs">Enable codecs for patent-encumbered audio
     and video formats.</flag>
   <flag name="screencast">Enable support for remote desktop and screen cast
     using <pkg>media-video/pipewire</pkg></flag>
   <flag name="suid">Build the SUID sandbox, which is only needed on
     CONFIG_USER_NS=n kernels</flag>
   <flag name="system-ffmpeg">Use system ffmpeg instead of the bundled one</flag>
   <flag name="system-icu">Use system icu instead of the bundled one</flag>
   <flag name="tcmalloc">Use tcmalloc designed for optimizing memory use and
     reuse.  Default in 91.</flag>
   <flag name="widevine">Unsupported closed-source DRM capability (required by
     Netflix VOD)</flag>
  </use>
</pkgmetadata>
