<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pkgmetadata SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/metadata.dtd">
<pkgmetadata>
  <maintainer type="person">
    <!-- Ebuild on the oiledmachine-overlay -->
    <email>orsonteodoro@hotmail.com</email>
    <name>Orson Teodoro</name>
  </maintainer>
  <upstream>
    <bugs-to>https://github.com/upscayl/custom-models/issues</bugs-to>
    <remote-id type="github">upscayl/custom-models</remote-id>
  </upstream>
  <use>
    <flag name="4xHFA2k">
      4x anime upscaler.  ESRGAN based.  Using the HFA2k dataset with OTF (on
      the fly degradation) jpeg compression and blur.  
    </flag>
    <flag name="4xLSDIR">
      A photo upscaler without degradation handling.  It uses a RRDBNet base
      model.  Trained with the the LSDIR dataset.
    </flag>
    <flag name="4xLSDIRCompactC3">
      A photo upscaler which handles a bit of jpeg compression.  It uses
      SRVGGNET compact model for faster inference times.  Trained with the LSDIR
      dataset.
    </flag>
    <flag name="4xLSDIRplusC">
      A photo upscaler which handles a bit of jpeg compression and blur.  It
      uses the RRDBNet base model.  Trained with the LSDIR dataset.
    </flag>
    <flag name="4xNomos8kSC">
      A 4k realistic photo upscaler handling jpeg compression.  It was trained
      with the the HAT network (small and large model).   Trained with Nomos8k
      dataset with OTF (on the fly degradation) jpeg compression and blur.
    </flag>
    <flag name="4x_NMKD-Siax_200k">
      A real world 4X upscaler for JPEG 75 quality and better using ESRGAN.
    </flag>
    <flag name="4x_NMKD-Superscale-SP_178000_G">
      A real world 4X upscaler for artifact free images using ESRGAN.
    </flag>
    <flag name="RealESRGAN_General_WDN_x4_v3">
      Lightweight faster but slightly worst quality of of the default model
      with a (WDN) Wide and Deep Network model.
    </flag>
    <flag name="RealESRGAN_General_x4_v3">
      Lightweight faster but slightly worst quality of the default model
      without a (WDN) Wide and Deep Network model.
    </flag>
    <flag name="realesr-animevideov3-x2">
      An optimized anime video model for X2 scaling
    </flag>
    <flag name="realesr-animevideov3-x3">
      An optimized anime video model for X3 scaling
    </flag>
    <flag name="realesr-animevideov3-x4">
      An optimized anime video model for X4 scaling
    </flag>
    <flag name="uniscale_restore">
      This model is designed to restore heavily compressed or noisy images.
      Trained with video game screenshots at 4k.
    </flag>
    <flag name="unknown-2_0_1">
      An model accidently used for Ultrasharp in the 2.0.1 upscayl release.

      For image comparison, see
      https://github.com/upscayl/upscayl/issues/324
    </flag>
  </use>
</pkgmetadata>
