<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pkgmetadwata SYSTEM "https://www.gentoo.org/dtd/metadata.dtd">
<pkgmetadata>
  <maintainer type="person">
    <email>orsonteodoro@hotmail.com</email>
    <name>Orson Teodoro</name>
  </maintainer>
  <!--

  oiledmachine-overlay notes:

  This ebuild currently is focused on mitigation of CPU hardware vulnerabilties
  focused on data tampering mitigation.

  It was created as a reaction to interest in perfect copy achiving and
  to provide a solution for archivists, legal, etc.

  A parent ebuild may be considered to verify larger mitigation coverage
  against data theft to verify that X sandboxes and LSM are installed.

  The optional sys-kernel/mitigate-dos can be used to protect perfect copy
  over network to mitigate against disruption.

  Build time environment variables:

  CUSTOM_KERNEL_ATOM - Name of the kernel you want to add to take advantage
  of automatic RDEPEND updates instead of manually updating/removing kernel
  packages.  If you set this, then disable USE=custom-kernel.  Multiple
  kernel packages may be specified.

  Example:

    CUSTOM_KERNEL_ATOM="sys-kernel/ot-sources sys-kernel/xanmod-kernel"

  FIRMWARE_VENDOR - Name of the CPU manufacturer for the kernel.  It should be
  set for cross compile builds since the builder CPU manufacturer could be
  different.

  -->
  <use>
    <flag name="aacraid">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the AAC RAID driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="ata">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the ATA driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="auto">
      Auto resolves firmware and kernel version required for full mitigation,
      instead of manually selecting microarchitecture which determines the
      minimum requirements for those 2 items which benefits mostly LTS
      configurations.

      This is recommended for Intel® CPUs since the USE flag coverage for
      microarchitectures is incomplete.
    </flag>
    <flag name="bfq">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the BFQ IO scheduler.
    </flag>
    <flag name="bluetooth">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the Bluetooth® subsystem.
    </flag>
    <flag name="bridge">
      Mitigate against data tampering for Ethernet bridge support.
    </flag>
    <flag name="btrfs">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the Btrfs filesystem.
    </flag>
    <flag name="cdrom">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the cdrom driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="cougar">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the Cougar 500K gaming
      keyboard.
    </flag>
    <flag name="custom-kernel">
      Prevent vendor lock-in when doing kernel mitigation checks.
    </flag>
    <flag name="enforce">
      Protect against data tampering by replacing vulnerable versions.
    </flag>
    <flag name="ext4">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the ext4 filesystem.
    </flag>
    <flag name="firmware">
      Use firmware as mitigation.
      (A BIOS firmware update from the motherboard manufacturer may still be
      required if the firmware package doesn't apply to your model.)
    </flag>
    <flag name="fscache">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the FS-Cache filesystem.
    </flag>
    <flag name="hfsplus">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the HFS+ filesystem.
    </flag>
    <flag name="hugetlbfs">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the hugetlbfs filesystem.
    </flag>
    <flag name="ice">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the E800 network driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="ima">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the IMA security module.
    </flag>
    <flag name="ipv4">
      Mitigate against data tampering in ipv4.
    </flag>
    <flag name="ipv6">
      Mitigate against data tampering in ipv6.
    </flag>
    <flag name="iwlwifi">
      Mitigate against data tampering in the iwlwifi driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="jfs">
      Mitigate against data tampering in the JFS filesystem.
    </flag>
    <flag name="kvm">
      Mitigate against data tampering in the KVM subsystem.
    </flag>
    <flag name="md-raid1">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the md/raid1 driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="mlx5">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the mlx5 network driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="mptcp">
      Mitigate against data tampering for Multipath TCP (MPTCP).
    </flag>
    <flag name="mt76">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the mt76 network driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="netfilter">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the netfilter firewall.
    </flag>
    <flag name="nfs">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the NFS server network
      filesystem driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="nilfs2">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the NILFS2 filesystem.
    </flag>
    <flag name="ntfs">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the NTFS3 filesystem driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="nvme">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the NVMe driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="rtw88">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the rtw88 network driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="samba">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the Samba network filesystem.
    </flag>
    <flag name="scsi-sd">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the SCSI disk driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="selinux">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the SELinux security module.
    </flag>
    <flag name="smack">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the SMACK security module.
    </flag>
    <flag name="squashfs">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the SquashFS filesystem driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="tipc">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the TIPC protocol.
    </flag>
    <flag name="tls">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the TLS protocol.
    </flag>
    <flag name="video_cards_amdgpu">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the amdgpu driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="video_cards_nouveau">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the nouveau video driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="video_cards_nvidia">
      Mitigate against data tampering, privilege escalation, Spectre V1,
      Spectre V2 for the NVIDIA® video driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="video_cards_v3d">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the v3d video driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="video_cards_vmware">
      Mitigate against data tampering for the vmwgfx video driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="vmware">
      Mitigate against data tampering for VMware support.
    </flag>
    <flag name="zero-tolerance">
      Bump to the latest patched kernel point releases when the changelog
      indicated fixed data tampering (DT) class of vulnerabilities.
      This will increase the coverage of DT mitigation for the installed
      kernels significantly because the USE flag coverage is incomplete
      or the vulnerability report doesn't clearly state the types of
      vulnerabilities.
    </flag>
  </use>
</pkgmetadata>
