<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pkgmetadata SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/metadata.dtd">
<pkgmetadata>
  <maintainer type="person">
    <email>orsonteodoro@hotmail.com</email>
    <name>Orson Teodoro</name>
  </maintainer>
  <longdescription>
    ot-sources is a kernel experimental patchset containing performance patches and encryption.
    Power users can choose either the BMQ, PDS, MuQSS CPU schedulers.
    The TRESOR patch provides increased mitigation from cold boot resistant attacks (only in the 4.14.x series).
    Compiler based optimizations are provided by GraySky patch and O3 patch.

    Currently not updated:
    The amd-staging-drm-next patches provide increase compatibility and better support for with new hardware
    and features.
    The ROCk kernel driver will install the driver needed for the ROCm platform.  ROCm requires PCIe 2.0.
  </longdescription>
  <upstream>
    <!-- for this patchset -->
    <bugs-to>https://github.com/orsonteodoro/oiledmachine-overlay/issues</bugs-to>
    <maintainer status="active" type="person">
      <!-- for bmq and pds -->
      <email>cchalpha@gmail.com</email>
      <name>Alfred Chen</name>
    </maintainer>
    <maintainer status="active" type="person">
      <!-- for muqss -->
      <email>kernel at kolivas dot org</email>
      <name>Con Kolivas</name>
    </maintainer>
    <maintainer status="active" type="person">
      <!-- for zentune patchset -->
      <email>jan.steffens@gmail.com</email>
      <name>Jan Alexander Steffens</name>
      <!-- aka heftig -->
    </maintainer>
    <maintainer status="active" type="person">
      <!-- for the bfq patchset -->
      <email>paolo.valente@linaro.org</email>
      <name>Paolo Valente</name>
    </maintainer>
    <maintainer status="active" type="person">
      <!-- for the linux kernel -->
      <name>Linus Torvalds</name>
    </maintainer>
    <maintainer status="active" type="person">
      <!-- for the linux kernel -->
      <name>Linus Torvalds</name>
    </maintainer>
    <maintainer type="project">
      <!-- for genpatches -->
      <email>kernel@gentoo.org</email>
      <name>Gentoo Kernel Project</name>
    </maintainer>
    <maintainer status="active" type="person">
      <!-- for graysky2 GCC patches -->
      <email>graysky AT archlinux DOT us</email>
      <name>graysky</name>
    <maintainer status="active" type="person">
      <!-- for tag releasing ROCk -->
      <name>Kent Russell</name>
    </maintainer>
    <maintainer status="active" type="person">
      <!-- for latest tag releases of amd-staging-drm-next -->
      <email>Anthony.Koo@amd.com</email>
      <name>Anthony Koo</name>
    </maintainer>
    <maintainer status="active" type="person">
      <!-- for tresor aes-ni and i386, 2010-->
      <email>tilo.mueller@informatik.uni-erlangen.de</email>
      <name>Tilo Mueller</name>
    </maintainer>
    <maintainer status="active" type="person">
      <!-- for tresor (aes-128) i386, 2012-->
      <email>johannes@jgoetzfried.de</email>
      <name>Johannes Goetzfried</name>
    </maintainer>
  </upstream>
  <use>
    <flag name="amd-staging-drm-next-latest">Patches the kernel with latest AMD GPU compatibility and fixes.  May break compile time anytime.</flag>
    <flag name="amd-staging-drm-next-milestone">Patches the kernel with the stable milestone release of AMD GPU compatibility and fixes.</flag>
    <flag name="amd-staging-drm-next-snapshot">Patches the kernel with the tested latest AMD GPU compatibility and fixes.</flag>
    <flag name="bfq">Patches the kernel with BFQ fixes and updates from the Liquorix kernel project.</flag>
    <flag name="bmq">Patches the kernel to use BMQ CPU scheduler, a more simple scheduler.</flag>
    <flag name="bmq-quick-fix">Patches the kernel with fixes to BMQ.</flag>
    <flag name="build">Builds the kernel.</flag>
    <flag name="cve_hotfix">Applies patches to resolve CVEs (Common Vulnerabilities and Exposures).</flag>
    <flag name="cfs">Assumes the IO scheduler will be the stock CFS CPU scheduler.</flag>
    <flag name="disable_debug">Installs scripts to disable debugging, tracing, verbose output or related code paths.</flag>
    <flag name="graysky2">Patches the kernel for more CPU microarchitecutures</flag>
    <flag name="directgma">Toggles the merging or removal of commits related to FirePro DirectGMA support.  Disabling it may reduces the code size a bit; make it less problematic to update the amdgpu-driver/amd-staging-drm-next part of ROCk.</flag>
    <flag name="muqss">Patches the kernel with Con Kolivas patchset and includes his skiplist based MuQSS CPU scheduler.</flag>
    <flag name="o3">Patches the kernel to allow for more aggressive O3 compiler optimizations.</flag>
    <flag name="pds">Patches the kernel with an alternative skiplist based scheduler.</flag>
    <flag name="rock-latest">Patches the kernel with additional Multi GPU enhancements with the latest version of ROCk.  May break compile time anytime.</flag>
    <flag name="rock-milestone">Patches the kernel with additional Multi GPU enhancements with the latest version of ROCk.</flag>
    <flag name="rock-snapshot">Patches the kernel with additional Multi GPU enhancements with the tested latest version of ROCk.</flag>
    <flag name="symlink">Updates the the /usr/src/linux symlink for every newer release.</flag>
    <flag name="tresor">Controls application of TRESOR.  AES keys are stored in registers instead of RAM.</flag>
    <flag name="tresor_aesni">Patches the kernel with cold boot resistant AES hardware accelerated AES-NI support.</flag>
    <flag name="tresor_i686">Patches the kernel with cold boot resistant AES using SSE for 32 bit systems.</flag>
    <flag name="tresor_sysfs">Builds the external key setting program.</flag>
    <flag name="tresor_x86_64">Patches the kernel with cold boot resistant AES using SSE for 64 bit systems.</flag>
    <flag name="uksm">Patches the kernel with the Ultra Kernel Samepage Merging, a type of page deduper algorithm.  Using it may be insecure.</flag>
    <flag name="zentune">Patches the kernel with Zen Interactive Tuning.</flag>
  </use>
</pkgmetadata>
