<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pkgmetadata SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/metadata.dtd">
<pkgmetadata>
  <maintainer type="person">
    <!-- Ebuild fork on the oiledmachine overlay -->
    <email>orsonteodoro@hotmail.com</email>
    <name>Orson Teodoro</name>
  </maintainer>
  <maintainer type="person">
    <!-- Ebuild originator -->
    <email>jer@gentoo.org</email>
  </maintainer>
  <longdescription>
    This is an ebuild fork for Node.js with SLOT support.

    LTS will allow casual developers and non rolling release cycle packages a
    chance to stay in the ebuild ecosystem.

    More info about LTS versions see:
    https://nodejs.org/en/about/releases/
    https://github.com/nodejs/release#release-schedule

    More info about EOL versions see:
    https://github.com/nodejs/release#end-of-life-releases

    v16 EOL is 2024-09-11
    v18 EOL is 2025-04-30
    v20 EOL is 2026-04-30
    v21 EOL is 2024-06-01

    The removal cycle is now delayed to better enjoy the product for those with
    longer compile times.  Minor versions before an announced security release
    or ebuilds older than 2 point releases in the same major version are removed
    without notice.


    Petition for SLOT support at https://bugs.gentoo.org/580698
    It has been an issue since 2016.

    The design is based on a multiplexer wrapper.

    Tentative additional packages:

      app-portage/nodejs (on the oiledmachine-overlay) for includes switch

    NPM packages that require multislot:

      Angular
      Vue.js

    The active implementation selected by app-portage/nodejs is granted
    /usr/lib64/node_modules which is symlinked to one of the directories above.

    It's recommended to install a package to the slot based on lowest required.

    Referencing /usr/includes/node is not multi-emerge or multi-compilation
    safe when packages with differing node_multislot_*  and requires a mutex in
    a new eclass, but runtime use of node is multi-process safe.

    It is save to use the same node_modules with different node but compliation
    must have special treatment.

    Certain USE flags should only be enabled for the highest SLOT; otherwise,
    you will get a merge conflict.  They are noted in the use flag section.

    If you run /usr/bin/node without the environmental variable NODE_VERSION, it
    will default to node the selected active from eselect nodejs (or the major
    version contained in node_version.h from the active symlink.

    The NODE_VERSION valid values are 16, 18 which are the Long Term Support
    (LTS) versions.

    Running NODE_VERSION=16 /usr/bin/node --version will show you node16's version.

    The PGO trainer can be extended with your own customized benchmark to
    optimize for typical use cases.  You must create a folder located at
    ${S}/benchmark/custom and it must have at least a createBenchmark() function
    having all of this created as a per-package user patch.  For additonal
    details, see

https://github.com/nodejs/node/blob/master/doc/guides/writing-and-running-benchmarks.md
https://github.com/nodejs/node/tree/master/benchmark#nodejs-core-benchmarks

    NODEJS_EXCLUDED_BENCHMARKS is a per-package envvar that can contain a space
    separated string of paths to exclude from testing whenever a broken
    benchmark is encountered or support for that particular benchmark is
    unfinished at the ebuild level.

    An additional user supplied script script called ${S}/pgo-custom-trainer.sh
    can be provided to install locally a per package(s) to run	benchmark for
    that package if it contains one.  All new npm packages to be trained must
    installed in ${S}/node_modules.  If the package doesn't contain a benchmark,
    then it is not suitable for PGO training.

    When selecting a nodejs_pgo_trainers_*, only select those that reflect
    typical use.  Choosing trainers that do not reflect typical use may increase
    unwanted binary size or may cause degraded performance.
  </longdescription>
  <use>
    <flag name="acorn">
      Install the acorn JavaScript parser.
    </flag>
    <flag name="custom-optimization">
      Override the default -O3 flag.
    </flag>
    <flag name="doc">
      It installs docs.  It should only be enabled for the highest request slot.
    </flag>
    <flag name="inspector">
      Enable the V8 inspector.
    </flag>
    <flag name="man">
      It installs man pages.  It should only be enabled for the highest request
      slot.
    </flag>
    <flag name="mold">
      Use the mold linker with non-commercial preconditions.
    </flag>
    <flag name="npm">
      Enable NPM package manager.  It should only be enabled for the highest
      request slot.
    </flag>
    <flag name="pax-kernel">
      Enable building under a PaX enabled kernel.
    </flag>
    <flag name="pgo">
      Enable profile guided optimization.  It will double build times.
    </flag>
    <flag name="snapshot">
      Enable snapshot creation for faster startup
    </flag>
    <flag name="system-ssl">
      Use system OpenSSL instead of the bundled one.
    </flag>
    <flag name="systemtap">
      Enable SystemTAP/DTrace tracing.
    </flag>
    <flag name="rN">
      Bump ebuild revision (INTERNAL USE ONLY)
    </flag>
  </use>
</pkgmetadata>
