<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pkgmetadata SYSTEM "https://www.gentoo.org/dtd/metadata.dtd">
<pkgmetadata>
  <maintainer type="person">
    <email>orsonteodoro@hotmail.com</email>
    <name>Orson Teodoro</name>
  </maintainer>
  <!--

  oiledmachine-overlay notes:

  This ebuild is for enforcement of Denial of Service (DoS) mitigations on
  a broader scope.  It was previously focused and still continues to support
  mitigation of DoS based CPU hardware vulnerabilties.  The ebuild will
  support client-side DoS mitigation or server-side DoS mitigation.

  At this time, the ebuild-package is optional and ebuilds do not require it
  in this overlay.  Admins may emerge this ebuild directly.

  A parent ebuild may be considered to verify larger mitigation coverage.


  Build time environment variables:

  CUSTOM_KERNEL_ATOM - Name of the kernel you want to add to take advantage
  of automatic RDEPEND updates instead of manually updating/removing kernel
  packages.  If you set this, then disable USE=custom-kernel.  Multiple
  kernel packages may be specified.

  Example:

    CUSTOM_KERNEL_ATOM="sys-kernel/ot-sources sys-kernel/xanmod-kernel"

  FIRMWARE_VENDOR - Name of the CPU manufacturer for the kernel.  It should be
  set for cross compile builds since the builder CPU manufacturer could be
  different.

  -->
  <use>
    <flag name="apparmor">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the AppArmor security module.
    </flag>
    <flag name="auto">
      Auto resolves firmware and kernel version required for full mitigation,
      instead of manually selecting microarchitecture which determines the
      minimum requirements for those 2 items which benefits mostly LTS
      configurations.

      This is recommended for Intel速 CPUs since the USE flag coverage for
      microarchitectures is incomplete.
    </flag>
    <flag name="bcrm80211">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the bcrm80211 network driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="bluetooth">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the Bluetooth速 subsystem.
    </flag>
    <flag name="bridge">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for Ethernet bridge support.
    </flag>
    <flag name="btrfs">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the Btrfs filesystem.
    </flag>
    <flag name="cougar">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the Cougar 500K gaming keyboard.
    </flag>
    <flag name="custom-kernel">
      Prevent vendor lock-in when doing kernel mitigation checks.
    </flag>
    <flag name="ext4">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the ext4 filesystem.
    </flag>
    <flag name="firmware">
      Use firmware as mitigation.
      (A BIOS firmware update from the motherboard manufacturer may still be
      required if the firmware package doesn't apply to your model.)
    </flag>
    <flag name="f2fs">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the F2FS filesystem.
    </flag>
    <flag name="max-uptime">
      Verifies defaults for security and compiler settings in order mitigate
      against deadlock or hard reset.
    </flag>
    <flag name="md-raid1">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the md/raid1 driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="md-raid5">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the md/raid5 driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="ice">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the
      Intel速 Ethernet Connection E800 Series Support network driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="iwlwifi">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the iwlwifi network driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="ipv6">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service in ipv6.
    </flag>
    <flag name="mlx5">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the mlx5 network driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="netfilter">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the netfilter firewall.
    </flag>
    <flag name="nfsd">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the NFS server network
      filesystem driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="nf_tables">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the nftables firewall.
    </flag>
    <flag name="rtw88">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the rtw88 network driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="samba">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for Samba network file system.
    </flag>
    <flag name="selinux">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the SELinux security module.
    </flag>
    <flag name="video_cards_amdgpu">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the amdgpu driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="video_cards_intel">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the Xe and i915 video drivers.
    </flag>
    <flag name="video_cards_nouveau">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the nouveau video driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="video_cards_nvidia">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the NVIDIA速 video driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="video_cards_v3d">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the v3d video driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="video_cards_vmware">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for the wmwgfx video driver.
    </flag>
    <flag name="vmware">
      Mitigate against Denial of Service for VMware support.
    </flag>
    <flag name="zero-tolerance">
      Bump to the latest patched kernel point releases when the changelog
      indicated fixed DoS class of vulnerabilities.  This will increase the
      coverage of DoS mitigation for the installed kernels significantly because
      the USE flag coverage is incomplete.
    </flag>
  </use>
</pkgmetadata>
